A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Affairs Program, Department Chronological Correspondence Files FA549
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Affairs Program, Department Chronological Correspondence Files
1978-1996
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA549
23.56 Cubic Feet 62 letter document containers
Scope and Contents
The collection contains department correspondence sent by Ford Foundation staff in the International Affairs Program as well as reports, grant status reports, and grant program action forms. The correspondence is typically notices of grant approvals or grant declinations on projects related to international law and the environment, international peace and security, international human rights, international economics and development, U.S. foreign policy, and relations with the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe.
The dates on each folder refer to the dates on the weekly correspondence control forms. The forms list names/initials of relevant personnel, the date individual staff reviewed the correspondence, and the date the weekly correspondence was collected. The weekly correspondence forms were used to collate correspondence at the end of each week. If a folder in this collection is called "Chrons, 1991 February 8-15," then you can expect to find correspondence, grant action forms, and reports sent and reviewed between February 1-15 (the week before the first date in the folder title). If there is no specific day mentioned in the folder title only the month (ex. 1992 April), then the correspondence control forms are missing. The correspondence control forms are not always accurate and correspondence from previous weeks and months may be found in neighboring folders.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series:
1. European and International Affairs (EIA) Correspondence
2. International Affairs Program (IAP) Correspondence
The series refer to the change of program area title that occured during Foundation restructuring in the early 1980s. The folders within the collection are arranged chronologically.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Related Materials
For International Affairs Program, Department Chronological Correspondence Files from April-December 1990, see Ford Foundation records, International Affairs Division, Program Staff Files (FA548), Series I.
Ford Foundation records, International Affairs Division, Program Staff Files (FA548), Series I.
Biographical / Historical
Segment One: International Activities of the Ford Foundation: An Overview
The Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare was first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 report of the Gaither Study Committee, Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (RAC Library, call letters 361.7 GAI ), which was commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the Foundation's future. Foundation Trustees launched Ford's international grantmaking activities in 1950 when they approved the committee's report and its embrace of peace, democracy, and freedom. Since then, the Foundation has tackled these goals using a variety of strategies and responding to changing contexts, from the Cold War to the 1989 fall of the Berlin Wall and beyond.
Toward the Foundation's aspirational goal, "the establishment of peace", its international activities have comprised a wide range of conceptual approaches and focus areas. These include international affairs, international studies, international understanding, arms control and disarmament, international law, international economic concerns, and overseas development in nearly every region of the world. Three distinct periods emerge for the international grantmaking defined by external contextual changes and internal changes in Foundation leadership and structures: the expansion era of 1950-1965; the transition and restructuring years of 1966-1988; and the post-1989 shift away from Cold War dichotomies. During each of the distinct historical periods the consistent objectives were: 1) to ensure freedom and democracy in developed countries; 2) to foster education and international understanding in all countries; and 3) to contribute to the social, economic, and political development of less developed countries.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
A portion of this collection was transferred to RAC in 2012 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2012:034. These chron files (January 1991-August 1996) were processed shortly after arriving at the RAC. Another set of material was transferred to the RAC by the Ford Foundation in 2019 and ingested by RAC as parts of Accessions 2019:012, 2019:028, and 2019:046. These materials (Chrons, 1978-1990) were added to the existing collection.
Eastern Europe; Ford Foundation; International affairs; International relations; Program development -- Ford Foundation; Security, International; Soviet Union
- European and International Affairs (EIA) Correspondence, 1978-1981; 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of chronologically arranged memoranda and correspondence that was collected weekly from European and International Affairs staff. The correspondence refers to grant proposals, grant evaluations, research competitions for grant funding, meetings, trips, conferences, program reviews, and administrative matters. The correspondence was written by the following staff (in approximate order names appear in the series): Francis (Frank) X. Sutton, Peter Ruof, Felice D. Gaer, Enid C. B. Schoettle, Bruce L. Bushey, Ruth D. Carter, Crauford Goodwin, Michael Nacht, Wendy Gatof, Jill Newsom, Ms. Serrano, Ms. Watts, Ms. Edwards, Veronica Bermudez, Adrianne Grunberg, Nelly Rivera-Marrero, Ms. Bullard, Ms. Resnick, and Charlotte Van Deusen.
  - Chrons, 1978 October 4-16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chrons, 1978 October 19-31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chrons, 1978 November 2-9 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chrons, 1978 November 16-29 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chrons, 1978 December 1-8 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chrons, 1978 December 19-28 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chrons, 1979 January 3-17 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Chrons, 1979 January 23-30 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Chrons, 1979 February 5-14 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Chrons, 1979 February 16-27 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Chrons, 1979 March 5-18 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Chrons, 1979 March 16-30 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Chrons, 1979 April 4-17 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Chrons, 1979 April 24-26 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Chrons, 1979 May 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Chrons, 1979 May 18-29 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Chrons, 1979 June 1-14 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Chrons, 1979 June 18-28 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Chrons, 1979 July 5-11 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Chrons, 1979 July 18-20 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Chrons, 1979 July 25-31 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Chrons, 1979 August 3-15 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Chrons, 1979 August 20-28 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Chrons, 1979 September 4-17 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Chrons, 1979 September 20-27 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Chrons, 1979 October 2-11 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Chrons, 1979 October 16-29 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Chrons, 1979 November 1-14 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Chrons, 1979 November 16-28 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Chrons, 1979 December 3-14 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Chrons, 1979 December 18-21 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Chrons, 1980 January 3-11 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Enid Schoettle's Chrons, 1980 September 30-October 31 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Chrons, 1980 October 22-31 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Chrons, 1980 November 10-24 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Chrons, 1980 December 1-8 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Chrons, 1980 December 12-23 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Chrons, 1981 January 5-12 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Chrons, 1981 February 2 (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Chrons, 1981 February 17-24 (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Chrons, 1981 March 9 (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Chrons, 1981 March 18-31 (Box 9, Folder 42)
  - Chrons, 1981 April 13-28 (Box 9, Folder 43)
  - Chrons, 1981 May 15 (Box 9, Folder 44)
  - Chrons, 1981 June 16-24 (Box 9, Folder 45)
  - Chrons, 1981 June-August (Box 10, Folder 46)
  - Chrons, 1981 September 18-25 (Box 10, Folder 47)
- International Affairs Program (IAP) Correspondence, 1985-1996; 2
  This series consists of chronologically arranged memoranda and correspondence that was collected weekly from the International Affairs Program staff. The corresponence refers to grant proposals, grant evaluations, research competitions for grant funding, meetings, trips, conferences, program reviews, and administrative matters. Correspondence from the following International Affairs Program staff (in approximate order names appear in the series): Enid C. B. Schoettle, Paul Balaran, Thomas O. Bayard, Gary G. Sick, Laurice H. Sarraf, Schwartz, Adrianne Grunberg, Nichol, Rossi, Walsh, Joyce Dickson, Debra Lamb, Ann and Harry Cavanaugh, Bikales, Nelson, Brian Urquhart, Janice Rhea, Stanley J. Heginbotham, Thomas Trebat, Karel Vosskuhler, Seamus O'Cleireacain, Shepard Forman, Margo Picken, Joseph Schull, Delilah King, Mahnaz Isapahani, Geoffrey Wiseman, Miriam Aukerman, Larry Cox, Lavinia Baumhoff, Christine Wing, Bernard Wasow, Marion Pendleton, Matthew Findlay, Mary DeCaro, and Edwin Rekosh.
  - Chrons, 1985 June 6-13 (Box 10, Folder 48)
  - Chrons, 1985 June 20-27 (Box 10, Folder 49)
  - Chrons, 1985 October 5-11 (Box 11, Folder 50)
  - Chrons, 1985 October 17-31 (Box 11, Folder 51)
  - Chrons, 1985 November 7-14 (Box 11, Folder 52)
  - Chrons, 1985 November 21 (Box 11, Folder 53)
  - Chrons, 1985 December 5 (Box 12, Folder 54)
  - Chrons, 1985 December 13 (Box 12, Folder 55)
  - Chrons, 1985 December 19-31 (Box 12, Folder 56)
  - Chrons, 1986 January 9 (Box 12, Folder 57)
  - Chrons, 1986 January 16 (Box 12, Folder 58)
  - Chrons, 1986 January 23-30 (Box 13, Folder 59)
  - Chrons, 1986 February 6-13 (Box 13, Folder 60)
  - Chrons, 1986 February 21-27 (Box 13, Folder 61)
  - Chrons, 1986 March 13-27 (Box 13, Folder 62)
  - Chrons, 1986 April 3-10 (Box 14, Folder 63)
  - Chrons, 1986 April 17-25 (Box 14, Folder 64)
  - Chrons, 1986 May 1-16 (Box 14, Folder 65)
  - Chrons, 1986 May 22-29 (Box 14, Folder 66)
  - Chrons, 1986 June 5-12 (Box 15, Folder 67)
  - Chrons, 1986 June 19 (Box 15, Folder 68)
  - Chrons, 1986 July 10-17 (Box 15, Folder 69)
  - Chrons, 1986 July 24-31 (Box 15, Folder 70)
  - Chrons, 1986 August 7-14 (Box 16, Folder 71)
  - Chrons, 1986 August 21 (Box 16, Folder 72)
  - Chrons, 1986 September 4-11 (Box 16, Folder 73)
  - Chrons, 1986 September 18-25 (Box 16, Folder 74)
  - Chrons, 1986 October 2-9 (Box 17, Folder 75)
  - Chrons, 1986 October 16-24 (Box 17, Folder 76)
  - Chrons, 1986 October 30 (Box 17, Folder 77)
  - Chrons, 1986 November 7 (Box 17, Folder 78)
  - Chrons, 1986 November 14 (Box 17, Folder 79)
  - Chrons, 1986 December 4 (Box 18, Folder 80)
  - Chrons, 1986 December 12 (Box 18, Folder 81)
  - Chrons, 1987 January (Box 18, Folder 82-83)
  - Chrons, 1987 February (Box 19, Folder 84)
  - Chrons, 1987 February 20 (Box 19, Folder 85)
  - Chrons, 1987 March 8-20 (Box 19, Folder 86)
  - Chrons, 1987 March 27 (Box 19, Folder 87)
  - Chrons, 1987 April 4-10 (Box 20, Folder 88)
  - Chrons, 1987 April 24 (Box 20, Folder 89)
  - Chrons, 1987 May 1-8 (Box 20, Folder 90)
  - Chrons, 1987 May 15-29 (Box 21, Folder 91)
  - Chrons, 1987 June 5-18 (Box 21, Folder 92)
  - Chrons, 1987 June 25 (Box 21, Folder 93)
  - Chrons, 1987 July (Box 21, Folder 94, Box 22, Folder 95)
  - Chrons, 1989 January 6-13 (Box 22, Folder 96)
  - Chrons, 1989 January 20 (Box 22, Folder 97)
  - Chrons, 1987 January 27 (Box 22, Folder 98)
  - Chrons, 1989 February 3-10 (Box 23, Folder 99)
  - Chrons, 1989 February 17 (Box 23, Folder 100)
  - Chrons, 1989 March 3-17 (Box 23, Folder 101)
  - Chrons, 1989 March 24 (Box 24, Folder 102)
  - Chrons, 1989 March 31 (Box 24, Folder 103)
  - Chrons, 1989 April 7 (Box 24, Folder 104)
  - Chrons, 1989 April 14 (Box 24, Folder 105)
  - Chrons, 1989 April 28 (Box 25, Folder 106)
  - Chrons, 1989 May 4 (Box 25, Folder 107)
  - Chrons, 1989 May 12 (Box 25, Folder 108)
  - Chrons, 1989 May 18 (Box 25, Folder 109)
  - Chrons, 1989 June 2-9 (Box 26, Folder 110)
  - Chrons, 1989 June 16 (Box 26, Folder 111)
  - Chrons, 1989 June 23-30 (Box 26, Folder 112)
  - Chrons, 1989 July 7 (Box 26, Folder 113)
  - Chrons, 1989 July 14-21 (Box 27, Folder 114)
  - Chrons, 1989 July 28 (Box 27, Folder 115)
  - Chrons, 1989 August 4-11 (Box 27, Folder 116)
  - Chrons, 1989 August 18 (Box 28, Folder 117)
  - Chrons, 1989 September 1-8 (Box 28, Folder 118)
  - Chrons, 1989 September 15 (Box 28, Folder 119)
  - Chrons, 1989 September 18-29 (Box 29, Folder 120)
  - Chrons, 1989 October 2-13 (Box 29, Folder 121)
  - Chrons, 1989 October 20-27 (Box 29, Folder 122)
  - Chrons, 1989 November 3-10 (Box 30, Folder 123)
  - Chrons, 1989 November 17 (Box 30, Folder 124)
  - Chrons, 1989 November 27 (Box 30, Folder 125)
  - Chrons, 1989 December 4 (Box 30, Folder 126)
  - Chrons, 1990 December 11 (Box 31, Folder 127)
  - Chrons, 1989 December 18 (Box 31, Folder 128)
  - Chrons, 1989 December 25 (Box 31, Folder 129)
  - Chrons, 1990 January 1 (Box 31, Folder 130)
  - Chrons, 1990 January 8-15 (Box 32, Folder 131)
  - Chrons, 1990 January 22-29 (Box 32, Folder 132)
  - Chrons, 1990 February 5-12 (Box 32, Folder 133)
  - Chrons, 1990 February 19-26 (Box 33, Folder 134)
  - Chrons, 1990 March 5 (Box 33, Folder 135)
  - Chrons, 1990 March 12 (Box 33, Folder 136)
  - Chrons, 1990 March 26 (Box 34, Folder 137)
  - Chrons, 1991 January 11 (Box 34, Folder 138)
  - Chrons, 1991 January 18 (Box 34, Folder 139)
  - Chrons, 1991 February 8-15 (Box 35, Folder 140)
  - Chrons, 1991 February 22-28 (Box 35, Folder 141)
  - Chrons, 1991 March 8-15 (Box 35, Folder 142)
  - Chrons, 1991 March 22 (Box 36, Folder 143)
  - Chrons, 1991 March 28 (Box 36, Folder 144)
  - Chrons, 1991 April 5-12 (Box 36, Folder 145)
  - Chrons, 1991 April 19-26 (Box 36, Folder 146)
  - Chrons, 1991 May 3-10 (Box 37, Folder 147)
  - Chrons, 1991 May 17-24 (Box 37, Folder 148)
  - Chrons, 1991 June 7 (Box 37, Folder 149)
  - Chrons, 1991 June 14 (Box 38, Folder 150)
  - Chrons, 1991 June 21-28 (Box 38, Folder 151)
  - Chrons, 1991 July 3-12 (Box 38, Folder 152)
  - Chrons, 1991 July 19-26 (Box 38, Folder 153)
  - Chrons, 1991 August 9 (Box 39, Folder 154)
  - Chrons, 1991 August 16-30 (Box 39, Folder 155)
  - Chrons, 1991 September 6-13 (Box 39, Folder 156)
  - Chrons, 1991 September 20 (Box 39, Folder 157)
  - Chrons, 1991 September 26-October 5 (Box 40, Folder 158)
  - Chrons, 1991 October 11-18 (Box 40, Folder 159)
  - Chrons, 1991 October 25-November 1 (Box 40, Folder 160)
  - Chrons, 1991 November 8-15 (Box 40, Folder 161)
  - Chrons, 1991 November 22-27 (Box 41, Folder 162)
  - Chrons, 1991 November 29-December 5 (Box 41, Folder 163)
  - Chrons, 1991 December 13-January 3 (Box 41, Folder 164)
  - Chrons, 1993 August 6 (Box 41, Folder 165)
  - Chrons, 1993 August 13-20 (Box 42, Folder 166)
  - Chrons, 1993 August 27 (Box 42, Folder 167)
  - Chrons, 1993 September 3 (Box 42, Folder 168)
  - Chrons, 1993 September 10 (Box 42, Folder 169)
  - Chrons, 1993 September 24 (Box 43, Folder 170)
  - Chrons, 1993 October 1-15 (Box 43, Folder 171)
  - Chrons, 1993 October 22-29 (Box 43, Folder 172)
  - Chrons, 1993 November 5 (Box 43, Folder 173)
  - Chrons, 1993 November 12-19 (Box 44, Folder 174)
  - Chrons, 1993 November 26-December 3 (Box 44, Folder 175)
  - Chrons, 1993 December 10 (Box 44, Folder 176)
  - Chrons, 1993 December 17-31 (Box 44, Folder 177)
  - Chrons, 1994 January 7 (Box 45, Folder 178)
  - Chrons, 1994 January 14 (Box 45, Folder 179)
  - Chrons, 1994 January 28 (Box 45, Folder 180)
  - Chrons (Duplicate File), 1994 February (Box 45, Folder 181)
  - Chrons, 1994 March (Box 46, Folder 182-183)
  - Chrons, 1994 April 1-8 (Box 46, Folder 184)
  - Chrons, 1994 April 15 (Box 46, Folder 185)
  - Chrons, 1994 April 22 (Box 47, Folder 186)
  - Chrons, 1994 April 29 (Box 47, Folder 187)
  - Chrons, 1994 May 6-20 (Box 47, Folder 188)
  - Chrons, 1994 May 13 (Box 47, Folder 189)
  - Chrons, 1994 May 27 (Box 47, Folder 190)
  - Chrons, 1994 June 3 (Box 48, Folder 191)
  - Chrons, 1994 June 24 (Box 48, Folder 192-193)
  - Chrons, 1994 July 1-8 (Box 48, Folder 194)
  - Chrons, 1994 July 15 (Box 48, Folder 195, Box 49, Folder 196)
  - Chrons, 1994 July 22 (Box 49, Folder 197)
  - Chrons, 1994 July 29 (Box 49, Folder 198)
  - Chrons, 1994 August 5-12 (Box 49, Folder 199)
  - Chrons, 1994 August 19-26 (Box 49, Folder 200)
  - Chrons, 1994 September 2-9 (Box 50, Folder 201)
  - Chrons, 1994 September 16-23 (Box 50, Folder 202)
  - Chrons, 1994 September 30 (Box 50, Folder 203)
  - Chrons, 1994 October 7-14 (Box 50, Folder 204)
  - Chrons, 1994 October 21-28 (Box 51, Folder 205)
  - Chrons, 1994 November 4 (Box 51, Folder 206)
  - Chrons, 1994 November 11-25 (Box 51, Folder 207)
  - Chrons, 1994 December 2-9 (Box 51, Folder 208)
  - Chrons, 1994 December 16 (Box 51, Folder 209)
  - Chrons, 1994 December 23-30 (Box 52, Folder 210)
  - Chrons, 1995 January 6-13 (Box 52, Folder 211)
  - Chrons, 1995 January 20 (Box 52, Folder 212)
  - Chrons, 1995 January 27 (Box 52, Folder 213)
  - Chrons, 1995 February 3 (Box 52, Folder 214)
  - Chrons, 1995 February 10-24 (Box 53, Folder 215)
  - Chrons, 1995 March 3-10 (Box 53, Folder 216)
  - Chrons, 1995 March 17-31 (Box 53, Folder 217)
  - Chrons, 1995 April 7-14 (Box 54, Folder 218)
  - Chrons, 1995 April 21-28 (Box 54, Folder 219)
  - Chrons, 1995 May 12-26 (Box 54, Folder 220)
  - Chrons, 1995 June 2 (Box 54, Folder 221)
  - Chrons, 1995 June 9-16 (Box 55, Folder 222)
  - Chrons, 1995 June 23 (Box 55, Folder 223)
  - Chrons, 1995 June 30-July 7 (Box 55, Folder 224)
  - Chrons, 1995 July 14 (Box 55, Folder 225)
  - Chrons, 1995 July 21 (Box 55, Folder 226)
  - Chrons, 1995 July 28-August 4 (Box 55, Folder 227)
  - Chrons, 1995 August 11-18 (Box 56, Folder 228)
  - Chrons, 1995 August 21-28 (Box 56, Folder 229)
  - Chrons, 1995 September 1-8 (Box 56, Folder 230)
  - Chrons, 1995 September 15 (Box 56, Folder 231)
  - Chrons, 1995 September 22-29 (Box 56, Folder 232)
  - Chrons, 1995 October 6-13 (Box 57, Folder 233)
  - Chrons, 1995 October 20-27 (Box 57, Folder 234)
  - Chrons, 1995 November 3 (Box 57, Folder 235)
  - Chrons, 1995 November 10 (Box 57, Folder 236)
  - Chrons, 1995 November 17-24 (Box 58, Folder 237)
  - Chrons, 1995 December 8-15 (Box 58, Folder 238)
  - Chrons, 1995 December 22-30 (Box 58, Folder 239)
  - Chrons, 1996 January 5-12 (Box 58, Folder 240)
  - Chrons, 1996 January 19 (Box 58, Folder 241)
  - Chrons, 1996 January 26 (Box 58, Folder 242)
  - Chrons, 1996 February 2-16 (Box 59, Folder 243)
  - Chrons, 1996 February 23 (Box 59, Folder 244)
  - Chrons, 1996 March 1 (Box 59, Folder 245)
  - Chrons, 1996 March 8-15 (Box 59, Folder 246)
  - Chrons, 1996 March 22 (Box 59, Folder 247)
  - Chrons, 1996 March 29 (Box 59, Folder 248, Box 60, Folder 249)
  - Chrons, 1996 April 5-12 (Box 60, Folder 250)
  - Chrons, 1996 April 19-26 (Box 60, Folder 251)
  - Chrons, 1996 May 3-17 (Box 60, Folder 252)
  - Chrons, 1996 May 24-31 (Box 60, Folder 253)
  - Chrons, 1996 June 7 (Box 61, Folder 254)
  - Chrons, 1996 June 21 (Box 61, Folder 255-256)
  - Chrons, 1996 June 28 (Box 61, Folder 257)
  - Chrons, 1996 July 12-26 (Box 61, Folder 258)
  - Chrons, 1996 August 2 (Box 62, Folder 259)
  - Chrons, 1996 August 9 (Box 62, Folder 260)
  - Chrons, 1996 August 16-23 (Box 62, Folder 261)
  - Chrons, 1996 August 30 (Box 62, Folder 262)
  - Memoranda, 1996 (Box 62, Folder 263)